בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף daf, *Daf* is י"ט *Yud Tet*.
We start at the bottom of י"א עמוד ב' *Yud Aleph Amud
Bet* and we are talking about the issues about what constitutes a,
what's required for a
מבוי mavoi *Mavoi* to make it permissible. I should say that yesterday
I slightly misstated the proof about, if you remember there was a
question very critical about whether the top of the צורת הפתח tzurat
hapetach. *Tzurat HaPetach*, whether the bars have to reach it and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* brought an issue from the whole discussion about the
arch.
I was describing the proof based by the way on רבי Rebbe.
מאיר *Rebbi Meir* who says that you imagine that it's carved out,
which is not such a good proof because maybe that's because of
his special principle of imagining that it's carved out. The real proof
was what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that everybody agrees that if
the arch goes up ten and is four wide, then it doesn't
matter that it arches above here. The arch is irrelevant. And the
point is well why doesn't it matter if you need the crossbeam
and you have the arching here, then even without רבי Rebbe. מאיר
*Rebbi Meir*'s special position that you imagine it carved out, the actual
physical top is over here. So in the standard arch that's the
point, that the actual physical top counts even though the posts are
lower down. Anyway that's our principle that we say that that works
and again more significantly, or equally maybe significantly, is that a צורת
הפתח tzurat hapetach, *Tzurat HaPetach* works according to the way we rule,
not the way the רמב"ם *Rambam* rules, even if most of it
is open and even if they're wider than ten אמות amot *Amot*,
which is what it really allows contemporary עירוב eiruv *Eruv*. Anyway now
we turn to the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* where there was a debate
about what you need by a מבוי mavoi. *Mavoi*. בית שמאי Beit
Shammai *Beit Shammai* said a לחי lechi *Lechi* and a קורה kora,
*Kora* and בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beit Hillel* said a לחי lechi
*Lechi* or a קורה kora, *Kora*. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wanted
to see that maybe that debate was that if you require both
it functions as a wall, whereas if you require one or the
other it functions as a היכר heker, *Hekker*. And the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* also wanted to understand what that means in terms of what's
biblically versus what's rabbinically required. And this is going to be the
ongoing theme for today, these two questions. Number one, the function whether
they're functioning as a wall or as a היכר heker, *Hekker*, and
number two, whether this is what's required to make it a biblical
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *Reshut HaYachid* or it's already a biblical רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid *Reshut HaYachid* and what's required in order to make
it allowed to carry. The simple sense is is that the three
walls of a standard dead-end מבוי mavoi *Mavoi* is sufficient for a
biblical רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *Reshut HaYachid* and what you need on
the fourth wall a לחי lechi *Lechi* or קורה kora *Kora* is
to allow it to be used rabbinically. But anyway the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* analyzed that based on the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel.
*Beit Hillel* and בית שמאי Beit Shammai, *Beit Shammai*. We will continue
with that today. So we pick up now three lines from the
bottom of י"א עמוד ב' *Yud Aleph Amud Bet* near the end
of the line, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rebbi Eliezer Omer*. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר לחיים lechayim *Rebbi Eliezer Omer Lichayayim*. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbi Eliezer* says two לחיים lechayim *Lichayayim*, not like בית
הלל Beit Hillel, *Beit Hillel* that either a לחי lechi *Lechi* or
קורה kora, *Kora*, not בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* that says a לחי
lechi *Lechi* and a קורה kora. *Kora*. He says two לחיים lechayim?
*Lichayayim*. איבעיא להו *Iba'ya Lehu*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says we
ask the question. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer לחיים lechayim וקורה קאמר *Rebbi
Eliezer Lichayayim Vekora Ka'amar*? When he says two לחיים lechayim. *Lichayayim* does
he mean the whole kit and caboodle, two לחיים lechayim *Lichayayim* and
the crossbeam, which
would certainly seem to indicate an idea of like making that fourth
wall like a real wall. או דלמא לחיים lechayim בלא קורה kora.
*O dilma Lichayayim Belo Kora*, or maybe it's a new position, two
לחיים lechayim. *Lichayayim* without the crossbeam. תא שמע *Tashma*, come in here,
we have a ברייתא braita. *Braita*. מעשה ברבי אליעזר שהלך אל רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose בן פרידא תלמידו *Ma'aseh BeRebbi Eliezer Shehalach El Rebbi
Yosi Ben Perida Talmido* to אובלין *Uvlin*, top of י"ב עמוד א'
*Yud Bet Amud Aleph*, to this place called אובלין *Uvlin*.
And so wait he wouldn't need two לחיים lechayim *Lichayayim* and the
קורה kora, *Kora*?
Yeah, which would mean a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach. *Tzurat HaPetach*, correct.
Then why wouldn't he have said that?
That's a good question. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
ומצאו *U'metza'o*, and he found his student שיושב במבוי שאין לו אלא
לחי lechi אחד *Sheyoshev BeMavoi She'ein Lo Ela Lechi Echad*, that he
was sitting in a מבוי mavoi, *Mavoi* that only had one לחי
lechi *Lechi*, even though he himself ruled you need two לחיים lechis,
*Lichayayim*. אמר amar: לו *Amar Lo*, he said to him, בני *Beni*,
my son, עשה לחי lechi. אחר *Asay Lechi Acher*, make another לחי
lechi? *Lechi* in order to make it permissible, presumably not on שבת
Shabbat *Shabbat*, but okay. אמר לו *Amar Lo*, so his student said
to him, וכי לסתום אני צריך *Vechisatom ani tzarich*, what do I
have to like seal off the entire wall? I mean come on,
two לחיים lechis. *Lichayayim*? אמר לו *Amar Lo*, he said, סתום ובכך
*S'tom u'vacha*, big deal, seal it off, yes that's what's required, don't
give me a hard time. Okay, אמר רבי Rebbe שמעון גמליאל *Amar
Rebbi Shimon Gamliel*, now at the end of this ברייתא braitia: *Braita*
says, says רבי Rebbe. שמעון גמליאל *Rebbi Shimon Gamliel*, לא נחלקו בית
שמאי ובית הלל על מבוי mavoi. שהוא פחות מארבע אמות amot שאינו
צריך כלום *Lo Necheleku Beit Shammai VeBeit Hillel Al Mavoi Shehu Pachot
Me'arba Amot She'eino Tzarich Kelum*. בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* and בית הלל
*Beit Hillel* don't argue if it's less than four אמות amot *Amot*
you don't need anything. In our משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* we had רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, *Rebbi Yishmael* saying that if it's less than four
אמות amot, *Amot* it's either a לחי lechi *Lechi* or קורה kora
*Kora* suffices and everybody agreed. Here רבי Rebbe שמעון גמליאל *Rebbi Shimon
Gamliel* is saying even a more extreme position, if it's less than
four אמות amot, *Amot* you don't need anything to make it permissible.
על מה נחלקו *Al Ma Necheleku*, what did they debate? על רחב
מארבע אמות amot ועד עשר eser *Al Rachav Me'arba Amot V'ad Esser*,
from four to ten אמות amot. *Amot*. שבית שמאי אומרים לחי lechi,
וקורה *SheBeit Shammai Omrim Lechi Vekora*, that בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* says
you need both a לחי lechi. *Lechi* and a קורה kora, *Kora*.
ובית הלל אומרים או לחי או קורה lechi o korah. *U'Beit Hillel
Omrim O Lechi O Kora*, either a לחי lechi *Lechi* or a
קורה kora, *Kora*. So the end is like our משנה Mishnah *Mishna*
except the end says less than four אמות amot. *Amot* you need
nothing, whereas our משנה *Mishna* says less than four אמות amot. *Amot*
one or the other. Anyway we're looking now at the beginning at
the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbi Eliezer*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this, תני מיהת *Tani Me'hat*, we teach nevertheless
in this ברייתא Baraita, *Braita*, וכי לסתום אני צריך *Vechisatom ani tzarich*,
that his student... Students responded to the position of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, that רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer demand was almost demanding like you
seal off the entire wall. אי אמרת בשלמא לחי וקורה Iy amarta
bishlama lechi vekora
if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you need two לחיים lechis. and
a קורה, kora, משום הכי אמר וכי לסותמו אני צריך. mishum hachi
amar vechi lesotmo ani tzarich. That's why he says, do you need
me to seal it off? Because then it clearly seems to be
functioning to be creating like an incomplete forced wall, because it's a
צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach אלא אי אמרת
לחיים בלא קורה, Ela iy amarta lechayim belo kora, if all he
required was two לחיים without the קורה, kora מאי לסותמו? mai lesotmo?
Why would he call that sealing it off? It's not sealing it
off, it's just a לחי lechi. on each side, which is not
the world's biggest question. It all depends on your, you know,
everything is relative based on what you thought was needed. So the
גמרא Gemara says, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, yeah, here's what he's saying:
וכי לסותמו בלחיים אני צריך? vechi lesotmo belechayim ani tzarich?
What, you need me to seal it off with לחיים? Meaning, although
he said seal it off, it did not necessarily mean צורת הפתח,
tzuras hapesach it just meant that he felt that רבי אליעזר's Rabbi
Eliezer demand was extreme. But again, it does not prove whether רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. says you need two לחיים and a קורה kora,
or just two לחיים. Clearly, simply, if there's a way to say
you need two לחיים and a קורה, kora it's called a צורת
הפתח. tzurat ha-petach, So the simple sense is that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer when he says two לחיים just means just that, two לחיים.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes to the position of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel quoted in this ברייתא. braita אמר
מר, Amar mar, so we taught, so quoting back to something we
said before. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
said רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
where am I? אמר מר, Amar mar, I just lost my place.
Oh, yeah, לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על מבוי שפחות מארבע
אמות שאינו צריך כלום, lo nechelku Beit Shammai u'Beit Hillel al mavoi
shepachot me'arba amot she'eino tzarich klum, they didn't debate if it's less
than four אמות amot you don't need anything, but they only debated
between four and ten. So the גמרא Gemara says, והנן תנן, ve'anan
tnan, in our משנה we have a different version of that. We
said in our משנה, משום רבי ישמעאל אמר תלמיד אחד לפני רבי
עקיבא, mishum Rabbi Yishmael amar talmid echad lifnei Rabbi Akiva, in the
name of רבי Rebbe ישמעאל, a certain student said in the name
of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על
מבוי
שפחות מארבע אמות שהוא ניתר או בלחי או בקורה, lo nechelku Beit
Shammai u'Beit Hillel al mavoi shepachot me'arba amot she'hu nitar o belchi
o bekora, for less than four אמות amot they agree either a
לחי lechi or a קורה. kora So here רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says that at less than four you don't
need anything. I don't understand what the big deal is, since the
whole question is debate about what the debate of בית שמאי and
בית הלל is, they're debating that tradition, so maybe there's a third
position that less than four אמות amot they didn't require anything. But
the גמרא Gemara wants to, I guess, not have too many different
possibilities, it wants to conflate them. So how do you hear, does
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel say they don't, you
don't require anything, in our משנה it says either a לחי lechi,
or a קורה. kora, So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב אשי,
amar Rav Ashi, said רב אשי, Rav Ashi, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar,
here is how you read it: אינו צריך, eino tzarich, when it
says that less than four you don't need anything, it doesn't literally
mean you don't need anything. It means אינו צריך לחי וקורה, eino
tzarich lechi vekora, you don't need that much. You don't need a
לחי lechi and a קורה, kora כבית שמאי, keBeit Shammai, like בית
שמאי, ולא לחיים כרבי אליעזר, velo lechayim keRabbi Eliezer, and you don't
need two לחיים like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer meaning everybody agrees less
than ארבע אמות, arba amot, you don't need to do anything extra,
not you don't need anything, but you don't need anything excessive. I
understand. אלא או לחי או קורה כבית הלל, Ela o lechi o
kora keBeit Hillel, you either a לחי lechi or a קורה kora
like בית הלל. Right, so that was pretty unconvincing, it sounds like
there's yet another opinion of what the debate was, but the גמרא
Gemara wants to conflate them and say when it says nothing, it
means you don't need anything excessive.
Okay, וכמה? vechama? Now the גמרא Gemara turns to the question: How,
if we say
less than four אמות, amot, does not need a לחי lechi, or
a קורה, korah it just needs one or the
other, how narrow can it get? Meaning is there a certain point
where it's so narrow that really everybody would agree you don't need
anything, if the opening of the מבוי mavoi was so narrow? וכמה,
vechama, until how narrow does it have to be that you still
need something? אמר רב אחלי ואיתימא רב יחיאל עד ארבעה, Amar Rav
Achli ve'iteima Rav Yechiel ad arba'ah,
until ארבעה arba'ah טפחים. tefachim. Once it's ארבעה arba'ah טפחים, tefachim, then
everybody agrees that that's almost like it's not a break at all,
everybody agrees ארבעה arba'ah טפחים tefachim or less. Yeah, I don't know,
it's not based on לבוד, lavud, but it's based on the fact
that then that's clearly almost self-defined itself just as a small door,
and everybody agrees that you don't really need anything. Okay now, אמר
רב
ששת אמר רב ירמיה, Amar Rav Sheshet amar Rav Yirmeyah, now by
the way I should say though that ארבעה arba'ah טפחים tefachim does
not necessarily mean that you've got an opening ארבעה arba'ah טפחים. tefachim.
If you have an opening ארבעה arba'ah טפחים, tefachim, then obviously it's
okay because you have something on each side. ארבעה arba'ah טפחים tefachim
doesn't need anything means it's a very narrow מבוי. mavoi. One wonders
how anybody, I mean it's a narrow alleyway. Length or width? No,
width, this opening here is ארבעה arba'ah טפחים, tefachim, which is like
what, like a foot? A very narrow alleyway. So it is interesting,
although this end is totally open, if it's narrow enough, everybody would
say that it does not require anything, which is again quite fascinating
because you would think that at least consistently you would need something
to define it as a fourth wall. Again, if the idea is
that this thing is really a היכר, heker. then you could say
that there's not as much of a need for a היכר, heker,
because it's so narrow, opens up into something wider, maybe it's more
obvious, and so on. But it is quite fascinating that there could
be a position where you don't, a size where you don't need
anything on the fourth wall. Yes.
Would the same apply like you know consider like a wall just
in general if you have houses that are less than four... is
it considered almost one wall?
No, we're not saying that less than four טפחים tefachim is לבוד.
lavud. Three טפחים tefachim is לבוד. lavud. We're just saying that in
the הלכה halacha that the fourth wall of a מבוי mavoi. of
an alleyway requires a לחי lechi or a קורה, korah and we
don't suffice with three walls, if the opening is narrow enough, we
do suffice with three walls. It's not saying a principle of לבוד.
lavud. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav
Sheshet, אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Amar Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba, אמר
רב: Amar Rav: מודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר. Modim Chachamim le-Rabbi Eliezer. Now,
since we just quoted the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
you require two לחיים, we're going to say that there is a
case where people agree with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that you do
require two לחיים. When is that? בפסי חצר. be-pas tze-chatzer. If you're
not talking about a מבוי, mavoi, you're talking about a חצר. chatzer.
You remember we said the other day, we never really explained why,
but we said the other day that a חצר, chatzer, the courtyard
that houses open into, requires more for their fourth wall. They might
require two planks on either side. And it's called a פס, pas,
not a לחי. lechi Now why is it called a פס, pas,
not a לחי? lechi You might remember yesterday we quoted the position
of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that says it has to be three
טפחים tefachim wide. So three טפחים tefachim wide is much more significant.
It's a plank, it's not just a stick. Okay, so by the,
by a חצר, chatzer, there's an assumption that a חצר chatzer needs
more than a מבוי. mavoi. Number one is the stick, the לחי
lechi has to be wider. It's not just a משהו, mashehu, it
has to be maybe three טפחים tefachim or wider, although we will
see opinions that even by a חצר chatzer a little bit is
enough. But there certainly are positions that by a חצר chatzer you
need something more substantial, which is why by a חצר chatzer it's
called a פס. pas. Number one. And number two, the possibility that
you need something on both sides. Now, why you need more by
a חצר chatzer is not so clear. It could be because a
חצר chatzer has many people using it. It has all the houses
using it, so it's much more commonly used. And there's much more
greater likelihood that people will carry in it, so maybe therefore they
required more. It could also be תוספות Tosafot says, although this is
ironic, but it's like maybe the reverse logic which we find sometimes,
that a מבוי mavoi opens up straight into a רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim. Now therefore you would say maybe you need more for a
מבוי. mavoi, But again, remember the גמרא Gemara at one point said
well that makes the contrast greater. So if the contrast is greater,
maybe you need
less. It's not
clear, but there clearly is a greater demand of that fourth wall
of a חצר. chatzer. So and that, that's what the גמרא Gemara
is saying, that everybody says we rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that says you require two לחיים. Where do we rule like it?
בפסי חצר be-pas tze-chatzer
by the planks at the side of a חצר chatzer as opposed
to a מבוי. mavoi There the חכמים Chachamim agree to רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer, רב נחמן Rav Nachman אמר: הלכה כרבי אליעזר Halacha ke-Rabbi
Eliezer בפסי חצר. be-pas tze-chatzer. I agree with you by a חצר
chatzer we require planks on both sides, but it's not like everybody
agrees to it, it's just there we rule like him. So the
ruling is the same, but not because it's unanimous, but because here
we'll rule like him. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak: מאן מודים? Man modim? רבי. Rebbe הלכה מכלל
דפליגי. Halacha mikh-lal de-pleegi.
When we say everybody agrees to רבי Rebbe אליעזר that you need
a plank on both sides, that's רבי. Rebbe, Because if you remember
we quoted this yesterday, the debate between רבי Rebbe, and the חכמים
Chachamim whether by a חצר chatzer you need a plank on both
sides or just on one side. So when he says people agree
to רבי Rebbe אליעזר by a חצר, chatzer, nobody's really... meaning, who
agrees to רבי Rebbe, אליעזר by a חצר? chatzer? רבי. Rebbe רבי
Rebbe, says by a חצר chatzer you need a plank on both
sides. Then the other position said הלכה, halacha, we rule like רבי
Rebbe אליעזר by a חצר, chatzer, מכלל דפליגי, mikh-lal de-pleegi, which suggests
that there's a debate even by a חצר. chatzer. So מאן פליגי
עליה? Man pleegi aleh? Who debates even by a חצר? chatzer? רבנן.
Rabbanan. It's the Rabbis. Means that there's a debate of רבי Rebbe
and the Rabbis whether a חצר chatzer needs a plank on both
sides or on one side. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא:
חצר, Chatzer, as opposed to a מבוי, mavoi. which is an alleyway
that the courtyards feed into, but the actual courtyards themselves, ניתרת בפס
אחד, niteret be-pas echad, one פס pas is enough. רבי אומר בשני
פסים, Rebbe omer bishnei pasim, two פסים. pasim. Okay, so here again,
the principle being without the גמרא Gemara ever really explaining it, that
a חצר chatzer demands more than a מבוי. mavoi Now the simple
sense is, as I said, is that a חצר chatzer is where
the houses open into, the מבוי mavoi is where the yard, the
חצר chatzer open into the מבוי, mavoy. into the alleyway, and the
alleyway opens to רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So for some reason the
חצר chatzer demands more. We will find at the end of today's
דף, and something we said before, that it's not even, the line
is not even so much functionally whether it's a yard or an
alleyway, but that anything that is more lengthwise than widthwise is halachically
defined as a street, as an alleyway. You know, conceptually, you think
of a street, it's something long, right? Thin and long. Whereas anything
that is square or that actually is
wider than it is long, which means like the flow of traffic,
you don't define length by the longest side, but you know, the
flow of traffic, it's wider than it is long, that is a
courtyard. Okay, so basically it winds up being not even functional, but
based on whether structurally it's basically seen primarily as long or primarily
as square or squat. And if it's a courtyard it requires more
than an alleyway. What's the more? So one position just says a
פס, pas, which sounds like a לחי, lechi, but we'll find out
that a פס pas might be wider than a לחי. lechi. Okay,
but that position is not... obviously that more, but then רבי Rebbe,
says you require a פס pas on both sides. So the גמרא
Gemara says when it comes to a חצר chatzer we have more
opinions like רבי אליעזר because רבי says by a מבוי mavoi you
need a לחי lechi on both sides, and here we're saying by
a חצר chatzer according to רבי, you need a פס pas on
both sides like רבי אליעזר, and it could be that even though
the Rabbis argue on רבי, at least according to some we rule
like רבי by a חצר. chatzer. So by a חצר chatzer we
clearly demand more. Right, what we'll see in a minute what the
difference might be between a פס pas and a לחי. lechi So
let's take a
look. אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebi Asi amar Rabbi
Yochanan, חצר צריכה שני פסים. chatzer tzericha shenei pasin. Like רבי, like
we just said, a חצר chatzer needs two planks, a plank on
each side. אמר ליה רב זירא לרבי אסי, Amar lei Rav Zeira
le-Rabbi Asi, so רב זירא Rav Zeira said to רבי אסי Rabbi
Asi who said this in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
מי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? Mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Does רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say that by a חצר, chatzer, by a
yard, you need planks on both sides? ואת הוא דאמרת משמיה דרבי
יוחנן, Ve-at hu de-amrit mi-shmeih de-Rabbi Yochanan, you yourself say in the
name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, עוביין otdam ארבעה. arba. That the planks have
to be four טפחים tefachim wide. Now that sounds like that's a
pretty serious requirement. Maybe that makes sense on one side. He doesn't
imagine that you would demand that if you're already demanding two sides.
וכי תימא Ve-khi teima now maybe you want to try to say
yes both are true, ארבע מכאן וארבע מכאן, arba mikan ve-arba mikan,
both it has to be four טפחים tefachim wide and you need
it on each side? והתניא? Ve-ha tanye? You can't say that. We
taught in a ברייתא, רבי אדא בר אבימי קמיה דרבי חנינא, Rabbi
Ada bar Avimi kamei de-Rabbi Chanina, רבי אדא בר אבימי Rabbi Ada
bar Avimi teaches, taught in front of רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, ואמרי
לה קמיה דרבי חנינא בר פפא, ve-amrei lei kamei de-Rabbi Chanina bar
Pappa, some say in front of רבי חנינא בר פפא, Rabbi Chanina
bar Pappa, and here's what he taught. קטנה בעשר וגדולה באחד עשר.
Ketannah de-eser u-gedolah be-achad asar. Remember this from yesterday one or a
few days ago, one חצר chatzer opening up into the other where
we say that the small one is ten
אמות, amot
right, we said one חצר chatzer opening into the other into a
big one, so this is ten אמות and this is eleven אמות.
Okay, width. And the reason this one is good is because it's
got a פס pas on each side. Okay, so if it has
a פס pas on each side and it's one אמה amah more,
that means three טפחים tefachim on each side. So there's no way
you can say that you require four טפחים tefachim for the פס
pas and you need two of them. You could say two of
them and less than four טפחים, tefachim, right, or you could say
four טפחים tefachim and you don't need two, and maybe it's something
like this and then this one only this one counts, but you
can't say you both need four טפחים tefachim and two of them.
That would not work with that description. Okay, so so you've got
a problem. I don't buy that you need both four טפחים tefachim
and you need two of them. So the גמרא Gemara isn't done.
כי סליק רב זירא מימי Ki salek Rabbi Zeira mi-yammei when רב
זירא Rav Zeira
came up from the ocean, he didn't answer. He didn't answer but
we're not done. פירשה Pirshah and he explained, ברוח אחת בארבעה. be-ruach
achat be-arba'ah. Okay if
you're right, it's either or. If you have a plank on one
side it has to be four טפחים. tefachim. משתי רוחות Mi-shetei ruchot
or you have a plank on both sides, משהו מכאן ומשהו מכאן.
mashehu mikan u-mashehu mikan. Then it's enough to have even a small
amount on either side. Okay, that's all very nice, that reconciles the
two statements of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but it doesn't explain the
idea of eleven and ten because that is that's you know, it's
more than four and it's more than a משהו mashehu on each
side. Why does what's that position that you need the bigger one
to be a whole אמה amah bigger? So והא דתני ve-ha de-tani
אדא בר אבימי Ada bar Avimi that teaching of אדא בר אבימי
Ada bar Avimi that the big one has to be an אמה
amah bigger, which is three טפחים tefachim on each side, so that's
רבי היא, Rebbi hi, that's רבי that yes says you need you
need a פס pas on each side. And not only that, וסבר
לה כרבי יוסי, ve-savar lah ke-Rabbi Yose, and he also like רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose because you'll remember that we quoted רבי יוסי yesterday
that says you need three טפחים tefachim on each side. So what
are we saying? We're saying that by a חצר chatzer you need
more than a מבוי. mavoi A מבוי mavoi a לחי lechi is
enough. By a חצר chatzer you might you need something on each
side according to רבי,
or there's another possibility which is take your pick. Either you have
something on each side and maybe that's a משהו mashehu which is
enough, or on one side but it has to be but it
has to then be something substantial, four טפחים. tefachim. Okay, so what
are basically the positions that we have? By a,
right, right, a מבוי mavoi or we'll just focus on בית הלל,
we say לחי, lechi oops, I don't know why I just wrote
there, לחי lechi או קורה. korah Okay and by a חצר chatzer
instead of a לחי lechi we call it a פס. pas. And
what do we mean by a פס? pas? So there's a couple
of possibilities, right? רבי says you need two and each one has
to be three טפחים, tefachim, right? That's רבי's position. And now we're
having רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position which is saying that you need
either two and a משהו, mashehu, or you need one but it
has to be four טפחים. tefachim. Okay but certainly more than a
לחי lechi which is just like a which is one and a
משהו. mashehu. Okay
here it's either two times three טפחים tefachim which is רבי, that's
the idea that said you had eleven and ten, right, so that
you would have three טפחים tefachim on each side. side or רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that we've now reconciled his two statements. One statement
said four טפחים. tfachim. So fine, if you're doing one it has
to be four טפחים, tfachim, if you're doing two it can be
a משהו. mashu. So we definitely have higher criteria by a חצר
chatzer than we have by a מבוי. mavoi... So let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with it. Okay, דתניא, de-tanya,
oh
we just did that. אמר רב יוסף אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל:
Amar Rav Yosef amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: חצר ניתרת בפס אחד.
chatzer niteres be-pas echad. A חצר, chatzer, one פס pas is enough.
Now how big is a פס? pas? Maybe it has to be
four טפחים? tfachim? It's not clear exactly. אמר
ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar leh Abaye le-Rav Yosef, so אביי Abaye
said to רב יוסף: Rav Yosef: מי אמר שמואל הכי? mi amar
Shmuel hachi? Did שמואל Shmuel really say one פס pas is enough?
והא אמר
ליה שמואל לרב חנניה בר שילא, ve-ha amar leh Shmuel le-Rav Chananya
bar Shila,
שמואל Shmuel said to רב חנניה בר שילא: Reb Chananya bar Shila:
את לא תעביד עובדא אלא או ברוב דופן, at lo ta'avid uvda
ella o be-rov dofen, and you don't act on it, don't do
a practical ruling by חצר chatzer unless that fourth wall is the
majority of the wall is walled in, או בשני פסין, o b-shnei
pasin, or with two planks. So how could you say שמואל Shmuel
says one plank is enough? Here he demands two planks or the
majority, which is certainly more than just a simple plank. אמר ליה,
amar leh, so he said back to him: ואנא לא ידענא דעובדא
הוה בדורא דרעותא? ve-ana lo yadana de-uvda hava be-Dura de-Ra'usa? Wait a
minute, but do I not know, you're telling me 'ah you know
two planks שמואל Shmuel says somewhere else two planks,' I know a
story! There was this village of the shepherds, לשון ים נכנס לחצר
הוה, leshon yam nichnas le-chatzer hava, and there was like a literally
a tongue of the ocean, a little tributary that ran off from
the ocean and you know entered into the that broke through or
entered into a side of the חצר, chatzer, ואתא לקמיה דרב יהודה,
ve-ata le-kamei de-Rav Yehuda, and it came in front of רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda who was a student of שמואל, Shmuel, so presumably this
is consistent with שמואל's Shmuel ruling, ולא אצריכו אלא פס אחד, ve-lo
atzricho ella pas echad, and he said one פס pas is enough.
So you're challenging me 'how did I say שמואל Shmuel say one
פס pas is enough? somewhere else שמואל Shmuel says two פסים,' pasim,
look there's a whole story here, they allowed it with one פס.
pas. אמר ליה, amar leh, so he said back to him: לשון
ים קאמרת? leshon yam qat-amart? Well, whoa whoa whoa, you're talking about
the like the water, the ocean? קלו שהקילו חכמים במים. kaloo she-heikilu
chachamim b-mayim. Don't prove me any ruling relating to the ocean. The
rabbis were lenient when it came to water, which means specifically what
they demanded to allow you to draw water, they lowered their demands
because obviously that was a pretty serious requirement, you don't have running
water. So what they demanded to allow it to consider that the
space that the water was in was a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid.
they were more lenient than in general.
I mean this is a sea wall, that didn't go join... what?
This is a sea
wall.
I don't know what... yeah, I don't know, maybe what לשון ים
leshon yam means. I also don't know how precisely they used the
word ים. yam. So
it's a good point, you know, it's that it is sea wa...
if it is sea water you're right, but the גמרא Gemara somehow
is assuming that they could draw from the water.
How do you know...
if it's a village it would be more like Lake Kinneret. A
what? If it were a shepherds' village it would be more likely
Lake Kinneret. Lake Kinneret, yeah, right, and they call Lake Kin...
right they call it the ים, yam, ים כנרת. Yam Kinneret. I
don't think ים yam means ocean specifically. Okay, how do I know
that they're lenient by water? דבעו מיניה רב טבלא מרב, de-ba'u mineih
Rav Tavla me-Rav, because רב טבלא Rav Tavla asked רב: Rav: מחיצה
תלויה מהו שתתיר בחורבה? mechitzah teluya mahu she-tatir be-churba?
If you have a suspended wall, will it allow you to carry
in like a you know in a dry ground underneath? אמר ליה,
amar leh, and he said back to him: אין מחיצה תלויה מתרת
אלא במים. ein mechitzah teluya materes ella be-mayim. It's only by water.
קלו שהקילו חכמים במים. kaloo she-heikilu chachamim be-mayim. It's a leniency by
water, which means what?
It means let's say, you know, here you are, you're in your
ship, okay,
and here's the water around you. Okay, what you can do on
your ship is you can basically hang a little booth over the
edge of your ship, which is ten טפחים, tfachim, and then you
lower your bucket down through there and you draw water. Okay, and
you imagine that this little booth that's hanging off the side of
the ship, these walls go down into the ocean and create a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. into the ocean. And that allows you to
draw water off the side of your ship. That is a מחיצה
תלויה. mechitzah teluya. It's suspended up in the air, but you imagine
it going straight down and defining the space below as a רשות
היחיד. reshus hayachid. If you had your house here and you had
a little you know balcony coming out and you wanted to draw
something from below and it wasn't water below, that we're not going
to allow. We allow the suspended מחיצה mechitzah for water, we don't
allow it for other things. So he says look, they're leniencies by
water. So don't go proving to me that there was water, a
little piece of the ocean or the lake that came into the
חצר chatzer and they allowed just one פס. pas. If they're trying
to do stuff to let you draw from the water, they're going
to be more lenient. But that doesn't prove in general a position
of what we need by a חצר. chatzer. And I still go
back to my question. How can you say that שמואל Shmuel says
one פס pas is enough if we know that שמואל Shmuel elsewhere
says you need two פסים? pasim? That's his question. Let's just see
the answer, then I'll take your question. So he says, so מכל
מקום קשיא *Mikal Makom Kashya*. So now we've got our contradiction. You're
teaching that he says one פס pas, *pas* and I have a
teaching that שמואל *Shmuel* says two פסין passin, *pasim*. So כי אתא
רב Rav. פפא רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע *Ki Ata Rav Pappa
Rav Huna Berei DeRav Yehoshua*, so רב פפא *Rav Pappa* and רב
הונא *Rav Huna* the son of רב יהושע *Rav Yehoshua* came מבי
רב *mibei Rav* from the house of רב *Rav*, פירשוה *pirshuha* they
explained it: מרוח אחת בארבעה *meruach achat bearba'ah*, משתי רוחות משהו mashehu?
לכאן ומשהו לכאן *mishtei ruchot mashu lekan umashu lekan*. Yes, when שמואל
*Shmuel* says one פס pas *pas*, one פס pas, *pas* if it's
big enough, going back to what we said here about רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*. So we had a problem, one place שמואל *Shmuel* says
one פס pas *pas*, one place he said two. When he said
one, if it's as big, if it's four טפחים Tefachim. *tefachim*, then
one is enough. When did שמואל *Shmuel* say two? If you only
have a משהו mashehu. *mashu* a little bit on each side. So
again we see that a חצר chatzer *chatzer* is more demanding by
a מבוי mavoi *mavoi*. A מבוי mavoi *mavoi* you have one and
it's a משהו mashu? *mashu*, by a חצר chatzer *chatzer* here we
have many positions
that you need two, or if we're going to let you use
one, it has to be something substantial, it has to be four
טפחים tefachim *tefachim*. Yes, Charles.
What is the logic behind the suspended partition above the water? Is
that because the water is going to be a כרמלית *karmelit*? Yes,
the water would be otherwise it would be a כרמלית *karmelit* and
it would be rabbinic carrying from a כרמלית *karmelit* to a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid *reshut hayachid*.
Correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so we're back
to this idea that you need more by a חצר chatzer. *chatzer*,
either two or one but it has to be four טפחים tefachim
*tefachim*. Is the water also considered like מן המוכן *min hamuchan*? Yeah,
I mean it's not not מן המוכן *min hamuchan*, what do you
mean? I mean it's like why can you turn on your faucet
on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*, right? Alright, so anyway, so now the גמרא
gemara. *Gemara* says like this, אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*, said
רב פפא *Rav Pappa*. Fish in the water would be בסדר *beseder*.
No, yeah, exactly, you're just trying to get the water. אמר רב
פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*, said רב פפא *Rav Pappa*, אי קשיא לי
הא קשיא לי i kasha li ha kasha li, *ee kashya li
ha kashya li*, if I've got a problem, here's the problem I
have, דאמר ליה שמואל לרב חנניה בר שילא *de'amar lei Shmuel leRav
Chananya bar Shila*, for שמואל *Shmuel* said to רב חנניה בר שילא
*Rav Chananya bar Shila*, this case we just said, לא תעביד עובדא
*la ta'avid uvda*, you don't actually rule that it's allowed by a
חצר chatzer, *chatzer*, אלא או ברוב דופן או בשני פסין *ela o
berov dofen o bishnei pasin*. Now we just said שני פסין *shnei
pasin* meant a little bit on each side and that's how we
reconciled it. One פס pas. *pas* if it's four טפחים tefachim *tefachim*,
שני פסין *shnei pasin* if it's a little bit. But now we
want to look at the other part of this statement: רוב דופן
*rov dofen*, the majority of the wall. למה לי רוב דופן *lama
li rov dofen*? Since when do you need a majority of the
wall? We just said that if you have one פס pas *pas*,
ארבעה *arba'ah* is enough. פס pas? ארבעה סגי *pas arba'ah sagi*.
We just got through saying that one plank if it's, two planks
it's a little bit on each side, if it's one, four טפחים
tefachim, *tefachim*. So what's he's talking about the majority of the wall?
וכי תימא מאי ברוב דופן *vechi teima mai berov dofen* many said
the
majority of the
wall what does it mean? בדופן שבעה *bedofen shiva*, we're talking about
a wall that's seven טפחים tefachim? *tefachim* wide. There, דבארבעה הוי ליה
רוב דופן *debe'arba'ah havay lei rov dofen*, and therefore he says רוב
דופן *rov dofen* which is a way of saying four טפחים *tefachim*
and it goes back to the idea of four טפחים *tefachim*. It
was just that case the four טפחים *tefachim* requirement happened to be
the majority of the wall. If that's what he's saying, but that
can't be, because if it really was only a seven טפח tefach.
*tefach* wall, למה לי ארבעה *lama li arba'ah*? Why would it need
four טפחים *tefachim*? Why not? בשלושה ומשהו סגי *bishlosha umashu sagi*. As
long as it was a little bit more than three it should
be enough. Why? Because if there was a seven טפח *tefach* wall
and you had a little bit more than three, it wouldn't be
the majority, it wouldn't be four טפחים *tefachim*, but what would you
be left with? What would be the left open space? If you
had seven that you closed off 3.1, what would be left with
the rest? 3.9 which is less than four. Remember what we said
before, which is less than four, everybody with four טפחים *tefachim*, you
wouldn't require anything. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is saying why are
you giving an example of saying the majority of the wall? Either
you require four טפחים *tefachim*, or you get the space to be
less than four, less than four. Why would you say you need
the majority of the wall? What's the logic there? Okay, so the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says, says and how do you know that it
should be enough to be even a little more than three if
it was seven טפחים *tefachim* wide? דאמר רב אחלי ואיתימא רב יחיאל
עד ארבעה *de'amar Rav Achlei ve'itaima Rav Yechiel ad arba'ah*, until four
טפחים *tefachim* but less than four טפחים *tefachim* you don't need anything.
So אי בעית אימא *ee bayit eima*, so we're back to the
question why he said the majority of the wall. So if you
want I can say כאן בחצר כאן במבוי *kan bachatzer kan bamavoi*.
When did we say that less than four you didn't need anything?
That was by a מבוי mavoi *mavoi*. Remember we're more lenient by
a מבוי mavoi *mavoi*. But by a חצר chatzer *chatzer*, less than
four is not sufficient. So in that case you really do need
the majority of the wall, or you need four טפחים *tefachim* that
the actual plank be that big. ואי בעית אימא *ve'ee bayit eima*,
and if you want I can say, דרב אחלי גופא תנאי היא
*deRav Achlei gufa tannai hi*, that's debated whether it's enough to be
less than four טפחים *tefachim*, maybe not everybody agrees on it. So
again what have we seen? We've seen here that this statement of
שמואל *Shmuel*, he said two, which would be a משהו *mashu*, one,
which would be four טפחים *tefachim* if you only have one. What
did he mean when he said רוב דופן *rov dofen*? So we
said רוב דופן *rov dofen* really was just an example of one
of them being four טפחים *tefachim*. Okay, and how about shouldn't it
be enough that you made the opening less than four? Isn't that
sufficient? And the answer is maybe not, maybe not everybody agrees that
when the opening is less than four, that's enough. What did he
mean when he said רודף? Rodef So we said רודף really was
just an example of one of them being four טפחים. Okay. And
how about shouldn't it be enough that you made the opening less
than four, isn't that sufficient? And the answer is maybe not, maybe
not everybody agrees that when the opening is less than four that
by itself suffices. Okay. Now the גמרא gemara goes back to goes
on to another related case. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabanan we taught. לשון
ים הנכנס לחצר Leshon yam hanichnas lechatzer similar to what we just
said before, you have a little piece of the ocean or the
lake whatever entering into a courtyard. אין ממלאין הימנה בשבת Ein memalin
heimena beshabbat you cannot draw water from it on שבת Shabbos אלא
אם כן יש לו מחיצה גבוהה עשרה טפחים ela im kein yesh
lo mechitza gevoha asara tefachim unless you have a מחיצה mechitza presumably
meaning a מחיצה mechitza on each side to wall off the forced
wall whatever's required, four טפחים on each side, you know, whatever you
require, you need something going on each side based on our earlier
discussion. במה דברים אמורים Bamei devarim amurim when is that true that
you need a wall on each side? שפרצתה ביותר מעשרה Shepirtzata beyoter
measara the opening is more than ten. Now again, it is very
frustrating because I haven't checked other גרסאות girsaot but certainly our print
גרסא girsa is very inconsistent about the use of the feminine and
the masculine because you know עשרה asara means עשרה טפחים asara tefachim
which is the height of the wall. But when we're talking about
how big the opening can be, our concern is whether it's more
than ten אמות. It should be עשר eser? not עשרה. asara. So
anyway, it's very confusing. It doesn't tell you, it doesn't what? אמות
עשר. Amot eser. You have אבל פרצתה ביותר מעשר? Aval pirtzata beyoter
meeser? ביותר מעשר. Beyoter meeser. You have עשר? eser. Oh, good for
you. So what did the שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz מעשרה? measara? You have עשרה?
asara? In the שטיינזלץ? Steinsaltz? Oh, that's שטיינזלץ, Steinsaltz, good. Okay, so
I have to check the manuscripts but at least this says עשרה.
asara. That says עשרה. asara. It should be עשר. eser. So how?
I don't know. Some of them have corrected the גרסא. girsa. It's
good. Okay, I'm not sure what the manuscript says but clearly it
should be עשר. eser? In this version it says עשרה. asara. The
גמרא gemara is very very regularly the printed גמרא gemara is inconsistent,
is not correct in its use of the grammar here which can
be very confusing. This גרסא girsa says עשר? eser? That says עשר?
eser Okay, good. Okay, alright, alright. Okay, והא דתניא Veha detanya anyway,
so when is it that you need to seal off that forced
wall? If the opening it is bigger than ten אמות. But עשרה
asara or עשר it should be, less than ten אמות it is
not a problem. Now, now the גמרא gemara has a question. ממלא
הוא דלא ממלאין. Memale hu delo memalin. Wait a minute, it says
that you need something special, an extra wall here if it's more
than
ten אמות in order to draw the water. So drawing the water
is the problem. הא טלטולי מטלטלינן Ha taltulei metalatlinan but it sounds
like there's never a problem even if it's bigger than ten אמות
you can carry in the חצר Chatzer,
even though it's
got this water that broke through the
wall. Why is that? והא נפרצה חצר במלואה למקום האסור לה Veha
nifretza chatzer bimlo'ah lemakom ha'asur lah but if it's
a bigger than
ten אמות, the חצר Chatzer has an opening into a place that
is forbidden to it because you can't carry
in the actual lake itself and you've got this break in the
wall of the חצר. Chatzer. So why should it be okay to
carry? Why is the only issue of making a wall in order
to allow you to draw the water? Carrying itself should be a
problem. So the גמרא gemara says here on the top of י"ב
עמוד ב', Yod Beit amud bet, הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha bemai askinan,
what are we talking about here? דאית ליה גידודא De'it leh giduda
that it has גידודא giduda which is remnants of a wall. Now
what the heck does that mean and why should that make it
better if it's for carrying versus for versus for drawing water? So
there's a big תוספות Tosafot trying to figure it out, but basically
the way רש"י Rashi understands the scenario is that right here you
basically had your wall on this side of the חצר, Chatzer whatever
it was, you had your wall and then it like broke here
and the whole wall didn't break, there was some remnant of the
wall, the water now sort of has come into the חצר Chatzer
like that. So the point is is that there really is enough
of a wall here, it's just covered up by the water, you
can't see it. Okay? So because the wall exists, you're allowed to
carry, you can carry in the courtyard because the courtyard actually has
walls around it. But to draw water, we're not going to let
you draw water if this is bigger than ten אמות unless you
actually make another מחיצה. mechitza. So again, okay, I get why you're
allowed to carry because there really is a wall, but what's the
big problem of drawing the water? Once there's a wall, why should
it be work to carry in the courtyard but not work to
let you draw the water, right? I still don't understand the difference.
So תוספות Tosafot has a couple of possibilities. One possibility is as
he says that what does תוספות Tosafot say? Says you've got your
houses here, hold on let me check תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says...
תוספות *Tosafos* says that the issue when we say you can't draw
water doesn't really mean you can't draw water. What it means is,
if you were to draw water, why would you draw water? Because
you'd want to go ahead and take the water back to your
house, right? So he says, if you're taking the water back to
your house, when you're carrying here and near your house, you can't
see the remnant of the wall over there. But when you're out
in the yard, then you can see the remnant of the wall,
which is a pretty funny, it redefines what the whole issue is,
to draw water or not. Another explanation תוספות *Tosafos* has, which is
maybe an easier one, is that if you're drawing the water and
this is an invisible wall down here, it's more likely that the
bucket will go over the wall and you'll carry from outside. So
that's our concern, that you're going to come carry outside. Anyway, תוספות
*Tosafos* has a couple of explanations why the wall would be good
enough to carry in here and not good enough to draw the
water. The easiest explanation, like I said, is that you might, if
you're drawing water, it might come to actually be, you know, going
from over the edge of the wall and therefore you need some
additional wall to make it obvious what the problem is.
Away from the edge of the wall?
What? What can I tell you?
They also have this before that they would be worried that like
you know because the sand was slope it would be too, oh
that the, that it would change the dimensions, תוספות *Tosafos* discusses that
as well. What does he say? Whatever, it's a special case that
we know that's not going to happen. Question?
Yes. This brings up an issue of whether an underwater wall really
counts as a מחיצה *mechitzah* for שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* purposes, such as
an old dam? Right.
Right. And we often do say that it does, you know, like
the, the wall of the ocean underneath and the, the coral reef
and we've talked about that, so it does. Anyway, so that's how
רשי *Rashi* explains the case that why this thing is really technically
okay, but if we want to let you draw water then we're
going to require that and it's bigger than ten אמה *amah*, we're
going to require you do something even in addition. All right, let's
continue now in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. I mean he has like
four different explanations in תוספות *Tosafos* why this thing should be good
for one and not good for the other. אמר רב יהודה Amar
Rav Yehuda. *Amar Rav Yehuda*, says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda: *Rav Yehuda*,
מבוי mavoi, שלא נשתתפו בו *Mavoi shelo nishtatfu bo*, now we're going
to a very nice direct conversation here about picking up what we
discussed at the end of yesterday, which is what constitutes a biblical
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid* as opposed to and whether this
thing that we're doing for the fourth wall, this לחי lechi, *lechi*
or קורה korah *korah*, is really making an additional wall or not
in a biblical way. So let's take a look. Says רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda *Rav Yehuda*, מבוי Mavoi שלא נשתתפו בו *Mavoi shelo nishtatfu
bo*, if you did not make a שיתוף shituf, *shituf* for the
מבוי Mavoi *mavoi*, everybody didn't join together with the loaf of bread,
okay, which is a rabbinic requirement. הכשירו בלחי Hechshiro b'lechi, *Hecheru belechi*,
if you added a לחי lechi? *lechi* as your fourth wall, then
הזורק לתוכו חייב hazorek letocho chayav, *hazorek letocho chayav*. Then it turned
it into a biblical רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid* and if
you throw into it from a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim. *reshus harabbim*
you're חייב chayav. *chayav*, meaning the לחי lechi? *lechi*, that makes two
assumptions. Number one is that biblically you need four walls to be
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshus hayachid* and the לחי lechi, *lechi*
turns, is a real fourth wall, even biblically speaking. הכשירו בקורה Hechshiro
b'kora, *Hecheru bekora*, if however for the fourth side you did not
use a לחי lechi, *lechi*, you only used a beam, then הזורק
לתוכו פטור hazorek letocho patur. *hazorek letocho patur*. It's not a biblical
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshus hayachid*, which means okay, if on the
one hand it says, and these two are intertwined ideas, how does
a לחי lechi *lechi* or how does a קורה korah *korah* function?
He says a לחי lechi *lechi* functions as a wall, a קורה
korah *korah* functions as a היכר heker. *heker*, and he says that
biblically only four walls is a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshus hayachid*.
So you make a לחי lechi *lechi*, you have real four walls,
you have a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *reshus hayachid*. You have a
קורה korah *korah*, you only have three walls, it's not a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid*. Of course the interesting position is that
then, no, didn't
you say שלא נשתתפו בו הכשירו בלחי *shelo nishtatfu bo hecheru belechi*,
therefore
if you were מכשיר *machshir* it, you made it legitimate by putting
up a לחי lechi. *lechi*, then you turned it into a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid*, הזורק לתוכו חייב hazorek letocho chayav. *hazorek
letocho chayav*. If you were, oh and what's it, from רשות הרבים
reshut ha-rabim. *reshus harabbim*. If you did, if you did a קורה
korah *korah*, now what's interesting is that he says that the rabbis
actually would let me carry in a courtyard that was not a
biblical רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid*. I have three walls and
a קורה korah, *korah* according to this, you then it doesn't have
four walls and the rabbis would still let me carry in it,
which is quite fascinating. We assume that you need a real רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid, *reshus hayachid* to be allowed to carry in it.
But that's what he's saying. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
change it. Let's keep on reading in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does like this. מתקיף לה רב ששת *Maskif
la Rav Sheshes*, רב ששת *Rav Sheshes* asks on this. טעמא דלא
נשתתפו בו *Taama delo nishtatfu bo*, you said all of this is
because you didn't make a שיתוף shituf *shituf*, everybody didn't join together
in the bread. הנשתתפו בו אפילו הכשירו בקורה נמי חייב chayav. *Hanishatfu
bo afilu hecheru bekora nami chayav*, does that mean to suggest that
if they joined in together with a שיתוף shituf. *shituf*, then even
with three walls it would become a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus
hayachid*? So now, הנשתתפו בו *Hanishatfu bo*, וכי כיכר זו עשאו רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid. ורשות הרבים *vechi kikar zu asao reshus hayachid vereshus
harabbim*, does this loaf of bread turn it into רשות היחיד reshut
ha-yachid *reshus hayachid* or רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim, *reshus harabbim*? Now you
know intuitively it's not such a crazy idea, we normally tell people
רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid, *reshus hayachid* רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim. *reshus harabbim*,
especially if you translate it private domain and public domain and you
assume that one of of the criteria is that ownership, that if
it's owned by the public, it could be a רשות הרבים, reshut
ha-rabim if it's owned privately, it could be a רשות היחיד. reshut
ha-yachid. So it sounds like he was saying if it only had
three walls, then unless you actually do a שיתוף, shituf it's gonna
not be a רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid. Sounds like if everybody joined
together, which is in a way of making it a type of
a privately owned domain, it would be a רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid,
But the גמרא Gemara rejects that because the גמרא says the definition
of רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid? has nothing to do with ownership. So
how could you say it matters whether they did a שיתוף shituf,
or not in terms of its identity?
We had that isn't it?
Let's say on the 11th? That's rabbinically. Biblically, it has nothing to
do with ownership. So how could you say it matters? So the
גמרא says וכי כיכר
זו עשתה רשות היחיד רשות הרבים? V'chi kikar zo asato reshus hayachid
reshus harabbim? Does this loaf do to determine its identity?
והתניא תנא בריתא. V'hatanya tuna baraita. חצרות של רבים, Chatzeiros shel rabbim,
if you have courtyards that are, you know, public courtyards, meaning many
houses opening into them, ומבואות שאינם מפולשים, umevoot she-einam mefulashim, or dead
end streets, בין עירבו ובין לא עירבו, bein eirvu u'vein lo eirvu,
whether you made a עירוב eiruv by the—again, עירוב eiruv means joining
together in the bread—or you did not, הזורק לתוכו חייב, hazorek le-tocho
chayav. they're רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid. So it has nothing to do
with whether you made this עירוב eruv or not, whether you joined
into the bread. Ownership has nothing to do with its identity as
רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid? is only about walls.
Again, we know that, but it's not a crazy הוה אמינא. hava
amina. Again, most people assume for רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid, it's got
to be privately owned. But the גמרא rejects that. So why are
you saying that it matters whether they joined in on the bread
or not? אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ela i itmar hachi itmar.
If it was taught, here's how it was taught. אמר רב יהודה.
Says רב יהודה: מבוי שאינו ראוי לשיתוף, Mavoi she-eino raui l'shituf, if
you have a מבוי Mavoi that you—it's not possible to do a
שיתוף. What מבוי Mavoi is it not possible to do a שיתוף
with? To join in together with the bread? If it's מפולש, mefulash,
if it's open at both ends. So he—so you're right. Actually, joining
in the bread does not change its biblical status. But if it's
the type of a מבוי Mavoi that that's not even possible, that
it's open at both ends, in that case: הכשירו בלחי, if you
made a לחי, lechi הזורק לתוכו חייב. Then you've made a third
wall and then you're חייב. הכשירו בקורה, if you made a קורה,
korah הזורק לתוכו פטור. hazorek le-tocho patur, You're פטור. patur. אלמא קסבר,
Alma kasavar, לחי משום מחיצה, וקורה משום היכר. Lechi mishum mechitza v'kora
mishum heker. You see a לחי lechi is a wall and a
קורה korah is a היכר. heker. So it's the same distinction he
said before, except here the point is a much more normal position.
The general assumption is that a biblical—let me repeat it again. The
general assumption is: a biblical רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid is three walls.
And what you need for the fourth wall is rabbinically in order
to allow you to carry. But biblically, it's three walls. So initially
the statement sounded like he said biblically you need four. Now we've
stepped back from that and we've gone to the more normal position.
Biblically you only need three. So if you have an open-ended מבוי
Mavoi that only has two walls, so now it's biblically not a
רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid it only has two walls. And you put
a לחי lechi on the third wall, לחי lechi counts as a
wall. Real biblical—it biblically has a status of a wall, and now
you have three walls and you have a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid.
If you only put a קורה, korah a קורה kora, does not
count as a wall. A קורה kora, is a היכר, heker? and
therefore it is not yet a רשות היחיד. By the way, if
this
idea—No, you cannot. No, to carry you need even more. You need
a צורת הפתח and the whole thing. Rabbinically, even a לחי lechi
is not enough to carry. But biblically, it makes it a רשות
היחיד. By the way, if this sounds strange, I will remind you
what we say by סוכה. Sukkah. Does anybody know what the הלכה
halacha is by סוכה? Sukkah? Two and a little wall. We say
שתיים כהלכתן ושלישית אפילו טפח. Shtayim k'hilchasam v'shlishis afilu tefach. Two normal
walls and the third even a little bit. So what here he
is saying is, essentially saying that that's the same for שבת. That
by שבת if you have two walls and a לחי, lechi which
is really like a 2.1 wall, that he says counts as three
walls for שבת. And that's his position. Three walls makes it a
biblical—doesn't allow you to carry. To carry you need, you know, like
a צורת הפתח and a לחי. lechi But biblically to be a
רשות היחיד, that is enough. Whereas if it's not a לחי lechi
but if it's a קורה, kora that doesn't count as a wall
at all. It actually has to be a לחי lechi and then
he says it's a biblical רשות היחיד.
So by putting a קורה kora. you've done nothing? Not biblically, not
rabbinically? What? By putting a קורה kora, you've done nothing?
Biblically you've done nothing. Right. That's exactly right. Exactly. So he says,
okay, so that's what he says. ורבא אמר. Rava amar. רבא Rava
says, I'm sorry, I skipped a line. לחי משום מחיצה וקורה משום
היכר. Lechi mishum mechitza v'kora mishum heker. וכן אמר רבה. V'chen amar
Rabbah. Same says, similarly says רבה. Rabbah. לחי משום
מחיצה lechi mishum mechitza, וקורה משום היכר. v'kora mishum heker. Same point.
ורבא אמר. Rava amar. רבא Rava says, אחד זה ואחד זה משום
היכר. Echad zeh v'echad zeh mishum heker.
No, they're both only a היכר. heker? So presumably in this case
two walls and a לחי lechi you would not have changed it
biblically, it would still not be a רשות היחיד. איתיביה
רב יעקב בר אבא לרבא. Aisivei Rav Yaakov bar Abba l'Rava. רב
יעקב בר אבא Rav Yaakov bar Abba asked רבא. Rava. הזורק למבוי,
Hazorek l'mavoi, if somebody threw into
a מבוי... Mavoi So if the לחי lechi is going to make
a difference biblically whether you’ve transgressed, it proves that a לחי lechi,
is a wall, because right, the only thing that biblically makes a
difference is if something counts as a wall or not. So you
see if a לחי lechi changes its biblical status a לחי lechi
functions as a wall. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is how you
have to read it, would say רבא Rava back. אינו צריך אלא
לחי, eino tzarich ela lechi, if it is only requires a לחי,
lechi what type of a מבוי Mavoi only requires a לחי? lechi
A מבוי Mavoi, that has, right, what type of a מבוי Mavoi
was permissible to carry in if you put up a לחי? lechi
A מבוי mavoy. that has three walls. So if it only needs
a לחי, lechi. it’s already has three walls, הזורק לתוכו חייב. Then
it’s a רשות היחיד and you’re חייב. לחי ודבר אחר, lechi ve-davar
acher, if it needs more than a לחי, lechi it has two
walls and in order to carry you would need both a לחי
lechi and a צורת הפתח, then הזורק לתוכו פטור, then you’re exempt.
So although the ברייתא on the face of it seemed to say
that a לחי lechi changes the status which biblically, which proves that
a לחי lechi is a wall, we said that’s not what it’s
referring to. It’s referring to if you have what do you have
prior to the לחי. lechi If you have three full walls it’s
a רשות היחיד, if you don’t have three full walls it’s not
a רשות היחיד. איתיביה, eisivei, so I’ll ask you again, says the
גמרא. יתר על כן אמר רבי יהודה, yeter al ken amar Rabbi
Yehuda, more than this other story which was they have like two
facing houses, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said the following, we quoted this
before. מבוי של שני בתים משני צידי רשות הרבים, עושה לחי מכאן
ולחי מכאן, או קורה מכאן וקורה מכאן, ונושא ונותן באמצע. mavoi shel
shenei batim mishenei tziddei reshut ha-rabim, oseh lechi mikan u-lechi mikan, o
korah mikan ve-korah mikan, ve-noseh ve-noten be-emtza. You can put either a
לחי lechi or a קורה kora on both sides and use the
middle street. אמרו לו, amru lo, and the rabbis said, אין מערבין
רשות הרבים בכך. ein me'arvin reshut ha-rabim be-kach. No, you cannot use
that to make an עירוב in a רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim Again
we’ve had this before, if you might remember, this is the famous
position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that makes it very easy to
carry in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim You basically have, here’s your
house, here’s your רשות הרבים, you’ve got your house here and your
house here, and he says if you want to carry in the
street here, all you have to do is put a לחי lechi
here and a לחי lechi here, or to put a קורה kora
here and a קורה kora. here and you can carry in a
רשות הרבים. Okay, and the rabbis said give me a break, that
is not enough to let you carry in a רשות הרבים by
just putting a לחי lechi or a קורה kora on both sides.
Okay, but what do you see from רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda presumably says that a לחי lechi or a קורה
kora really counts as a wall. Okay, so that’s according to him,
which is now by the way a challenge to the previous, because
until now we’ve been saying at most a לחי lechi counts as
a wall. He says a לחי lechi or a קורה really seals
it off, at least according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So let’s
see what the גמרא says.
So the גמרא says התם, hatam, no, it’s not because he holds
a לחי or קורה counts as a wall, because anyway the rabbis
argue. So what does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda hold? התם קסבר רבי
יהודה שתי מחיצות דאורייתא. hatam kasvar Rabbi Yehuda shtei mechitzot d’Oraita. That’s
because he really holds the two walls were already a רשות היחיד.
So he really felt that biblically it’s already a רשות היחיד, but
that does not prove that if we biblically require three or four
walls, it does not prove whether a קורה or a לחי would
function as the third or fourth wall. Okay, so yes רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is very lenient, but that’s because he really holds only
require two walls to begin with.
Yeah, but still, I mean if rabbinically you require a third wall,
then you still have...
no, maybe only rabbinically you require a היכר. heker? Honestly how do
you know? Okay, so the גמרא says like this. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מבוי, mavoy okay, so now
that is the end for that for now, but again this is
a recurring theme in the גמרא and I just want to repeat
it again, which is two very central questions. Number one, what biblically
makes a רשות היחיד? Three walls, four walls, two walls? We have
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says two walls, so he allows even
this crazy רשות הרבים case. We have the possibility the גמרא said
yesterday and said again today that biblically you need four walls to
be a רשות היחיד. The standard opinion is biblically you need three
walls to be a רשות היחיד and rabbinically to allow you to
carry we need something for the fourth wall, either a לחי or
a קורה, but biblically you only need three walls. Then you have
the other question, which is how does the לחי or the קורה
function? Does it function as a wall or does it function as
a היכר? heker On the one hand that’s a question if you
biblically have three walls, how do you understand what the fourth thing
is doing? Is it a wall or a היכר? And as we’ve
seen in this גמרא it could have biblical implications if you have
two walls and a לחי, does that turn it into a biblical
רשות היחיד? Is a לחי functioning as a wall or as a
היכר? Okay, so those are the two questions: what biblically makes רשות
היחיד, two, three, or four walls? The general assumption is three walls
is a רשות היחיד biblically, rabbinically to carry you need something for
the fourth, and then the other issue is how does the לחי
function? How does the קורה function? Where the גמרא seems to be
inclining to the idea that a קורה is a היכר and a
לחי is actually
a could be actually.
Biblically we don't distinguish between מבוי mavoy, חצר, Chatzer correct. But that
actually is the perfect segue because now the גמרא gets back to
this מבוי mavoy, חצר Chatzer distinction. So let's take a look. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, says רב יהודה
in the name of רב. מבוי שארכו כרחבו, Mavoi she'archo kerachbo, if
you have a מבוי mavoy that is that the length is equal
to the width, meaning it's square, okay, so it is not longer
than it is wide. And now this is what I've already told
you in advance that once it is not longer than it is
wide it's going to be defined as a חצר. Chatzer So you
have a courtyard that is not longer than it is wide,
אינו ניתר בקורה טפח. eino niter bekora tefach.
A קורה, did I skip a line? אינו ניתר בלחי משהו. eino
niter belechi mashehu. It is not even a small לחי is not
enough. It has a הלכה halacha of a חצר Chatzer, and it
needs a פס, pas like we said before, four טפחים or two
פסין, but a simple לחי is not enough. אמר רב חייא בר
אשי אמר רב, Amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi Amar Rav, so now
another statement which is basically doesn't disagree, just gives the other side
of the coin. מבוי שארכו כרחבו, Mavoi she'archo kerachbo, similarly if a
מבוי its length is the same as the width, it is not
longer than it is
wide, אינו ניתר בקורה טפח. eino niter bekora tefach. A קורה, the
beam, normally what's the width of the beam that we demand is
a טפח. Here that's not sufficient. What you do need is not
clear, but the basic point is it stops being a מבוי and
is considered a חצר Chatzer once it is square or wider, once
it is not longer than it is wide. And as we've already
seen a חצר Chatzer demands more. It needs a פס pas not
just a לחי. And now the גמרא is going to say the
following. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zera, כמה נכוונין שמעתא דסבי. kama
nechuvanin shmaita desavi. How like well-aligned this is actually not sarcastic. Sometimes
it could be sarcastic, but here it's not. Like how on the
mark is this teaching of the elders, that they said that it
changes its status. כיון שארכו כרחבו, keivan de'archo kerachbo, once its length
is the same as its width, once it is not longer than
it is wide, הוי ליה חצר, hava lei chatzer, it now is
defined as a חצר Chatzer because the normal sort of configuration of
a חצר Chatzer is something that's wider than long. A street is
longer than it is wide. וחצר אינה ניתרת בלחי וקורה. vechatzer eina
niteret belechi vekora. A חצר, Chatzer a לחי or a קורה is
not enough, as we've been saying, אלא בפס ארבע, ella bepas arba,
you need a פס, pas? ארבע, arba, four טפחים at least on
one side, or you need a little bit on each side. So
basically he's saying yes, it becomes defined as a חצר Chatzer once
its physical configuration changes. In a way there's an interesting parallel to
the earlier discussion about the שיתוף, which is don't think that like
function or ownership defines identity. You might have thought רשות היחיד רשות
הרבים is defined by whether it's how it's owned, right? No, no,
no, it's all defined by number of walls, you know, רשות היחיד.
You might have thought that the difference between a חצר Chatzer and
a מבוי is how it's used. A מבוי is a street, a
חצר chatzer. is a courtyard. No, it's all defined by its physical
configuration. Is it longer or is it wider? So there's this parallel
that we're defining it in these very objective structural terms and not
in functional terms. So once it is no longer longer than wide,
it's a חצר chatzer. and it needs a פס pas not a
לחי or a קורה. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zera, now said
רב זירא, Rav Zera, אי קשיא לי הא קשיא לי,
if I've got a question here's the question I have. דהוי האי
לחי כפס משהו ונישתרי. dehavi hai lechi kepas mashehu venishteri.
I don't get it. I get that it's a חצר chatzer and
a חצר needs a פס. pas, But so what? Why can't a
לחי count as a פס משהו? What's the difference between a לחי
or פס? They're just an extension. So the גמרא says אישתמיטתיה, ishmetiteih,
he forgot what we've just been saying for you know for 20
minutes ago. הא דאמר רב אמי אמר רבי יוחנן, hada amar Rav
Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan, פסי חצר צריכין שיהא בהן ארבע. pasei chatzer
tzrichin she'yehe bin arba. No, the whole difference between a פס and
a לחי is that a פס needs ארבע, arba, four טפחים, a
לחי can be a משהו. Okay. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman,
נקיטינן, naktiinan,
we take the position. איזהו מבוי שניתר בלחי וקורה, Eizu mavoi sheniter
belechi vekora, what's a מבוי that we're more lenient by and we
say either a לחי or a קורה, does not need a פס?
כל שארכו יתר על רחבו, kol she'archo yeter al rachbo, if its
length is more than its width. ולא עוד, velo od, and not
only that, ובתים וחצרות פתוחין לתוכו. u-batim vechatzerot petuchin letokho.
Here actually we do make a functional demand, not just structural, or
this is somewhat structural, but anyway, to be defined as a מבוי,
as an alleyway, not only does it have to be longer, but
it has to have yards open into it and houses opening into
the yard. That's the normal structure. House opens into a yard, yard
opens into an alleyway. So if it has those three features, houses
into yard, yard into the alleyway, and it's longer than it is
wide, then it has the lenient status of a מבוי and a
לחי or a קורה is enough. ואיזו היא חצר שאינה ניתרת בלחי
וקורה אלא בפס ארבע? Ve'eizu hi chatzer she'eina niteret belechi vekora ella
bepas arba?
And what is the חצר that we're saying has a greater demand
and לחי and קורה is not enough, it needs a real פס
of ארבע, arba, four טפחים? כל שמרובעת, kol she-meruba'at,
anything that's square. So the גמרא says מרובעת אין עגולה לא? meruba'at
in agula lo? What? Only square, not circular? Haven't you heard of
like these circular courts? So the גמרא says no, no, no, I
don't mean square as opposed to circles. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, here's
what I mean. אי ארכה יתר על רחבה. Ee orcha yeter al
rachba.
If it's longer than its wide, it's a מבוי. ומבוי בלחי וקורה
סגי, Umavoy belechi vekora sagi,
and a מבוי is enough with a לחי or קורה. ואי לא,
Ve'ee lo, and if it's not longer than its wide, הוי ליה
חצר, havlei chatzer, it's a חצר. So I don't mean it has
to be square. It could be circle, it could be trapezoidal, it
could be triangular, I don't care. What I mean is that if
it's not longer than its wide. In order to be a מבוי,
it has to be longer than it is wide. If it's not,
it's a חצר. וכמה? Vekamah? Now,
how much? Rashi says this means for it to be a מבוי,
how much longer does it have to be than wide? What? Just
like even a משהו? So סבר שמואל למימר savar Shmuel lemeimar עד
פי שניים ברחבה. ad pi shenayim berachba.
It has to be twice as long as it is wide to
be a street. Really, who knows of any street that's not much
longer than it is wide? So he had quite a very high
demand. So אמר ליה רב, amar lei Rav, no. הכי אמר חביבי,
Hachi amar chavivi, here's what my friend says, which is רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya, אפילו משהו, afilu mashu, even a tiny bit. So as
long as it's a little bit longer than wide, it's a מבוי
and a לחי or a קורה is enough. But as soon as
it's square or wider, then it's a חצר and then we require
much more, we need a פס, a לחי or a קורה does
not suffice. Alright. Like a circular whatever it is. What?
What are you saying? You're lost?
Ha! This wasn't so hard compared to other days.
Some of them were just going back.
I will tell you.